<manpage id="pullparser" cat="pullparser" title="pullparser">
  <namesection>
    <name>tDOM::pullparser</name>
    <desc>Create an XML pull parser command</desc>
  </namesection>

  <synopsis>
    <syntax>package require tdom

    <cmd>tDOM::pullparser</cmd> <m>cmdName</m> <o>?-ignorewhitecdata</o>
    </syntax>
  </synopsis>

  <section>
    <title>DESCRIPTION </title>    
    
    <p>This command creates XML pull parser commands with a simple
    API, along the lines of a simple StAX parser. After creation,
    you've to set an input source, to do anything useful with the pull
    parser. For this see the methods <m>input</m>, <m>inputchannel</m>
    and <m>inputfile</m>.</p>

    <p>The parser has always a <m>state</m>. You start parsing the XML
    data until some next state, do what has to be done and skip again
    to the next state. XML well-formedness errors along the way will
    be reported as TCL_ERROR with additional info in the error
    message.</p>

    <p>The pull parsers doesn't follow externial entites and are XML
    1.0 only, they know nothing about XML Namespaces. You get the tags
    and attribute names as in the source. You aren't noticed about
    CDATA Sections, comments, processing instructions and entities;
    they are silently ignored for you.
    </p>

    <p>On the brighter side is that character entity and attribute
    default declarations in the internal subset are respected (because
    of using expat as underlying parser). It is probably somewhat
    faster than a comperable implementation with the SAX interface.
    It's a nice programming model. It's a slim interface.
    </p>

    <p>If the option <o>-ignorewhitecdata</o> is given, the created
    XML pull parser command will ignore any white space only (' ', \t,
    \n and \r) text content between START_TAG and START_TAG / END_TAG.
    The parser won't stop at such input and will create TEXT state
    events only for not white space only text. </p>

    <p>The valid methods of the created commands are:</p>
    <commandlist>
      <commanddef>
        <command><method>state</method></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>input</method> <m>data</m></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>inputchannel</method> <m>channel</m></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>inputfile</method> <m>filename</m></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>next</method></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>tag</method></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>attributes</method></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>text</method></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>skip</method></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>find-element</method> <m>tagname</m></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>reset</method></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><method>delete</method></command>
        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>
    </commandlist>
  </section>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>XML</keyword>
    <keyword>pull</keyword>
    <keyword>parsing</keyword>
  </keywords>
</manpage>
